YESENIA ROMÁN

Contact	Summary
(939) 207 -8641 romanloyesenia@gmail.com Los Angeles, CA	I am a creative, resourceful, and bilingual librarian with over seven years of experience in reference, data acquisition, and cataloging services at large research institutions, and most recently at a public library. I enjoy helping people conduct re- search, learn, and make discoveries.
Education	
May 2015	M.S. in Library and Information Sciences Data Curation specialization University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign
May 2012	B.A. in Mesoamerican and Caribbean Anthropology University of Puerto Rico, San Juan
Professional experience	
June 2022 - Nov 2022	General Services Librarian, Part-time Inglewood Public Library, Main Library, Inglewood, CA.
	 Provided reference services and technological assistance for patrons of all ages. Developed and led community programming to engage and educate the public. Curated book displays to showcase the collection. Designed promotional materials for programs, events, and social media.
April 2021- Aug. 2021	Research Librarian Prof. Curtis Deutsch Computational Laboratory, University of Washington (Remote, contract-based)
	 Conducted a systematic literature review in Proquest and Web of Science for laboratory measurements of marine species thermal growth curves. Created a database of measurements extracted from published articles, tables, and figures. Organized citations and sources on Zotero shared library.

Professional experience cont.

Jan. 2019 - Oct. 2020

Research Librarian II (Data Services Specialist II) Institute for Health Metrics and Evaluation, Seattle, WA

- Provided reference services for six-plus research teams, including assistance with research questions, library materials, resources, catalogs, and other library tools.
- Data acquisition for six-plus research teams, leading to authorship in a peer-reviewed scientific article.
- Acquired and cataloged hundreds of data sources in different languages and formats.
- Advised and taught researchers best practices of data management and seeking.
- Established relationships with global vendors, researchers, and data providers in English and Spanish, leading to long-lasting data sharing and research collaborations between diverse organizations.

Jan. 2017 - Jan. 2019

Research Librarian I (Data Services Specialist I) Institute for Health Metrics and Evaluation, Seattle, WA

- Managed the Institute's Help Desk, including supervising task delegation and resource allocation for 6 librarians
- Provided reference services for six-plus research teams, including assistance with research questions, library materials, resources, catalogs, and other library tools.
- Data acquisition for three annual studies by six-plus research teams, leading to my authorship in five peer-reviewed scientific articles.

Dec. 2015 - Jan. 2017

Data Curator Institute for Health Metrics and Evaluation, Seattle, WA

- Dataset archiving in multiple formats and languages for an online public access catalog (GHDx) to ensure user agreement compliance.
- Managed Institute's catalog journal taxonomy by performing monthly reviews, additions, and merges.
- Biannual data source updates.

Nov. 2015 - Dec. 2015

Digital Content Curator Market.Space Inc, (Remote)

- Reviewed and created metadata for news articles on travel, venture capital, and gaming to train a machine-learning algorithm.
- Documented observations for taxonomy development and review.

Professional experience cont.

Jun. 2015 - Aug. 2015

UX Research Assistant Library of Congress: Office of Strategic Initiatives, Washington DC.

- Created metadata (Dublin Core) for library records to facilitate discovery by identifying trigger terms from popular searches in the loc.gov catalog.
- Assisted the main information architect for congress.gov to revamp, schedule and conduct user interviews.

Aug. 2013 – May 2015

Graduate Assistant University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign, IL

- Assisted library patrons in accessing and discovering information via email, phone, chat, and in person.
- Oversaw reference collection development projects.
- Developed research subject guides in the Social Sciences and Education disciplines.
- Created content for the unit's website using Dreamweaver and OpenCMS.
- Supervised student assistants.

March 2013 - July 2013

Special Education Paraprofessional Chicago Tech Academy, Chicago IL

- Taught students with special needs in the subjects of economics, media (photoshop and HTML), and algebra.
- Provided emotional support and reassurance to create a safe space for learning.
- Served as a translator (English to/from Spanish) in parent-social worker meetings.

Skills

- Bibliographic research
- Cataloging
- Documentation
- Excel/Google Sheets

- Illustrator/Procreator/Canva
- Metadata
- Reference
- Web design, HTML & CSS (e.g., https://jlpenn.github.io/index.html)

Professional development	
Oct. 2019	Introduction to Illustrator Seattle Central Community College - Seattle, WA
Oct. 2017	Front-end Development HTML, & CSS certificate University of Washington - Seattle, WA
June 2015	Digital Humanities Summer Institute University of Victoria, Victoria, BC
Conferences	
2020	Code(4)lib, 2020: Open Data Barriers that Persist at the Institutional Level. Ian Pollock, Yesenia Roman, Erica Leigh Slepak. Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania (Poster)
2011	Society for Applied Anthropology, 2011 : Women, Food and Identity in the Changing Socioeconomic Environment of Rural Oaxaca, Mexico. Seattle, Washington (Poster)
2011	Leadership Alliance National Symposium, 2011 : Breast-feeding Patterns and its relationship to Socio- Demographic Factors in American Samoa. Providence, Rhode Island (Poster)
Awards	
2015	Association of Research Libraries: Initiative to Recruit a Diverse Workforce Scholarship
Languages	
	English (Fluent)Spanish (Native)
Publications	
2022	The Next 'Great Dying' Is Coming for Your Seafood. Gizmodo. (Illustration)
2022	Rapid Reductions In Greenhouse Gas Emissions Are Critical For Avoiding A Major Mass Extinction Of Ocean Species .Forbes. (Illustration)

Peer-reviewed publications	
2021	Tobacco Use and Initiation among Young People in 204 Countries and Territories, 1990–2019. The Lancet. Public Health, 2021, pp. The Lancet. Public health, 2021–05. (Acknowledgement)
2018	Lim, Stephen S, et al. Measuring Human Capital: a Systematic Analysis of 195 Countries and Territories, 1990–2016. The Lancet (British Edition), vol. 392, no. 10154, 2018, pp. 1217–1234. (Authorship)
2018	GBD 2017 Risk Factors Collaborators. Global, regional, and national comparative risk assessment of 84 behavioural, environmental and occupational, and metabolic risks or clusters of risks for 195 countries and territories, 1990–2017: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2017. The Lancet (British edition), 2018-11-10, Vol.392 (10159), p.1923-1994 (Authorship)
2017	GBD 2015 Tobacco Collaborators. Smoking prevalence and attributable disease burden in 195 countries and territories, 1990–2015: a systematic analysis from the Global Burden of Disease Study 2015. The Lancet (British edition), 2017, Vol.389 (10082), p.1885-1906. (Authorship)
2017	GBD 2016 Risk Factors Collaborators. Global, regional, and national comparative risk assessment of 84 behavioural, environmental and occupational, and metabolic risks or clusters of risks, 1990–2016: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2016. The Lancet (British edition), 2017-09-16, Vol.390 (10100), p.1345-1422. (Authorship)
2017	GBD 2015 Risk Factors Collaborators. Global, regional, and national comparative risk assessment of 79 behavioural, environmental and occupational, and metabolic risks or clusters of risks, 1990-2015: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2015. Lancet. 2016 Oct 8;388(10053):1659-1724. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(16)31679-8. Erratum in: Lancet. 2017 Jan 7;389(10064):e1. (Authorship)
2016	Hmwe H Kyu, et al. Physical Activity and Risk of Breast Cancer, Colon Cancer, Diabetes, Ischemic Heart Disease, and Ischemic Stroke Events. BMJ, 2016-08-09, Vol.354, p.i3857-i3857. (Acknowledgement)